William H. Nebergall research and academic files, 1947-1973 C420
Indiana University Archives
William H. Nebergall research and academic files
1947-1973
Indiana University Archives
Nebergall, William Harrison, 1914-1978
C420
.8 cubic feet 2 boxes
William H. Nebergall was a faculty member in the Department of Chemistry at Indiana University from 1949-1975. Along with Joseph Muhler and Harry Day, his research led to the patenting of stannous fluoride, the first decay-preventing ingredient used in Crest toothpaste. Nebergall also conducted research in conjunction with the Office of Naval Research and the United States Public Health Service. This collection contains contracts, grants, research reports and proposals, and patents related to Nebergall's research. Also included is material pertaining to his academic career at Indiana University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
William H. Nebergall was born in Cuba, Illinois on December 12, 1914. He received a Bachelor of Education degree from Western Illinois State Teachers College in 1939 and completed a M.S. degree in chemistry in 1939. This was followed by teaching appointments in chemistry at State Teacher's College in Johnson City, Tennessee until 1941. During the 1941-1942 academic year he taught chemistry at the University of Kentucky, and from 1942-1944 he taught chemistry at the University of Minnesota. While at Minnesota, he completed his Ph.D.
In 1940, William Nebergall married Florence Eileen Johnson. The couple had two sons prior to Nebergall receiving a position at Indiana University in 1949, and a daughter was born a few years thereafter. He began his career at IU as an assistant professor of chemistry, and was promoted to associate professor in 1955.
Nebergall authored many publications and was an active researcher. He collaborated with fellow professor F.C. Schmidt to write a combination textbook and laboratory manual. This resulted in two widely used textbooks, College Chemistry and General Chemistry. Nebergall's research interests were in organogermanium chemistry and the chemistry of organosilicon compounds. Beginning in 1950, he worked with Joseph C. Muhler and Harry C. Day in their study of fluorides in relation to dental caries. Financial support from Proctor and Gamble for research on products to prevent tooth decay led to their development of the basic composition for what would come to be the anti-decay ingredient used in Crest toothpaste. Many patents were made in Nebergall's name for compounds created during this research.
In 1959, Nebergall was awarded a National Science Foundation faculty fellowship, which prompted him to take a sabbatical leave to conduct research in Germany. His health began to decline dramatically after his time in Germany. After years of ill health, he retired early at age 61 in 1975. He died in September 1978.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series: Research files and Academic files.
Scope and Content Note
This collection spans the years 1947-1973 and is organized into two series: Research files and Academic files, both of which are organized alphabetically by folder heading.
The first series, Research files, is dated 1947-1967 and contains materials relating to Nebergall's research in the field of chemistry. There is one folder with information about the National Science Foundation faculty fellowship he received in 1959. There are also contracts and reports for research he conducted in conjunction with the Office of Naval Research in the 1950s. His work with Proctor and Gamble is also represented through research proposals, patents, and technical reports. Grants from the United States Public Health Service, and reports generated from the research funded by those grants, are also included in this series.
Academic files, the second series, spans the period from 1949-1973. The first folder contains Nebergall's faculty annual reports from 1949-1973. There are two folders with correspondence, building reports, and other materials dated 1956-1970, all pertaining to an addition to the Chemistry Building. Also included is the 4th edition of his chemistry textbook authored with Frederic Schmidt and Henry Holtzclaw, Jr. Finally, there is a folder containing Nebergall's application materials for sabbatical leave.
Separated Material
Two photographs of Nebergall have been removed and transferred to the University Archives Photograph Collection.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 2003/128
Provenance
This collection was separated from the Indiana University Department of Chemistry records which were transferred from the Chemistry Department to the University Archives in 2003.
Chemists --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Indiana University. Department of Chemistry -- Faculty -- Archives; Nebergall, William Harrison, 1914-1978 -- Archives
- Research files, 1947-1967; undated (Box 1)
  - National Science Foundation faculty fellowship, 1960 (Box 1)
  - ONR (Office of Naval Research), 1952-1957 (Box 1)
    - Contracts, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - Proctor and Gamble, 1947-1967 (Box 1)
    - R groups attached to Si, 1949-1967 (Box 1)
      General
      (2 photographs removed)
    - Reports, 1947-1964; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Research proposals, 1953-1957; undated (Box 1)
    - Tin (II) chlorofluorides, 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - USPHS (United States Public Health Service), 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Grants, 1958-1963 (Box 1)
- Academic files, 1949-1973; undated (Box 2)
  - Annual reports, 1949-1973 (Box 2)
  - Chemistry building addition, 1956-1970; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General Chemistry, 4th edition, by William H. Nebergall, Frederic C. Schmidt, and Henry F. Holtzclaw, Jr., 1972 (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical leave, 1958-1959; undated (Box 2)